Let me tell you a story
دعوني أخبركم قصة
about a little girl named Naghma.
عن فتاة صغيرة تدعى (نغمة)
Naghma lived in a refugee camp
عاشت (نغمة) في مخيم للاجئين
with her parents and her eight brothers and sisters.
مع أبويها و أخوتها و أخواتها الثمانية.
Every morning, her father would wake up
و في كل صباح، يستيقظ أبوها
in the hopes he'd be picked for construction work,
على أمل أن يحظى بعمل في مجال البناء،
and on a good month he would earn 50 dollars.
و في أحسن الأحوال، يكسب 50 دولاراً في الشهر.
The winter was very harsh,
كان الشتاء قاسٍ جداً،
and unfortunately, Naghma's brother died
و لسوء الحظ، فإن أخا (نغمة) توفي
and her mother became very ill.
فألمّ بأمها وعكة صحية
In desperation, her father went to a neighbor
ووسط حالة من اليأس، قصد أبوها الجار
to borrow 2,500 dollars.
ليقترض منه 2,500 دولار.
After several months of waiting,
و بعد عدة شهور من الانتظار،
the neighbor became very impatient,
نفذ صبر الجار،
and he demanded that he be paid back.
و طلب إعادة الأموال التي دفعها.
Unfortunately, Naghma's father didn't have the money,
و لسوء الحظ، لم يكن لدى والد (نغمة) المال الكافي،
and so the two men agreed to a jirga.
و اتفق الرجلان على اللجوء إلى "جيرغا"
So simply put, a jirga is a form of mediation
و لتوضيح الصورة أكثر، فإن جيرغا هو شكل من الوساطة
that's used in Afghanistan's informal justice system.
يستخدم في نظام العدالة غير الرسمي في أفغانستان.
It's usually presided over by religious leaders
يترأسه في العادة زعماء دينيون
and village elders,
و كبار القرية،
and jirgas are often used in rural countries like Afghanistan,
و تستعمل مجالس الجيرغا غالباً في الدول الريفية كأفغانستان.
where there's deep-seated resentment
حيث هناك نقمة متجذرة
against the formal system.
ضد النظام الرسمي.
At the jirga, the men sat together
و في الجيرغا، جلس الرجال معاً
and they decided that the best way to satisfy the debt
و قرروا أن أفضل طريقة لإيفاء الدين
would be if Naghma married the neighbor's 21-year-old son.
ستكون بزواج (نغمة) من ابن الجار و الذي يبلغ من العمر 21 عاما.
She was six.
كان عمرها ست سنوات.
Now, stories like Naghma's unfortunately
الآن، لسوء الحظ فإن قصصاً كقصة (نغمة)
are all too common,
شائعة جداً،
and from the comforts of our home,
و من رغد العيش في بلادنا،
we may look at these stories as another
ربما ننظر إلى هذه القصص على أنها
crushing blow to women's rights.
لكمة أخرى قاضية لحقوق المرأة.
And if you watched Afghanistan on the news,
و إن شاهدتم أفغانستان على الأخبار،
you may have this view that it's a failed state.
ربما تعتقدون بأنها دولة فاشلة.
However, Afghanistan does have a legal system,
على أية حال، فإن أفغانستان تملك نظاماً تشريعياً،
and while jirgas are built on long-standing tribal customs,
و بينما تبنى مجالس الجيرغا على عادات قبلية متواجدة منذ زمن،
even in jirgas, laws are supposed to be followed,
حتى في الجيرغا، من المفترض أن يتم اتباع القوانين،
and it goes without saying
يتم الأمر دون القول
that giving a child to satisfy a debt
بأن إعطاء طفلة للإيفاء بالدين
is not only grossly immoral, it's illegal.
هو أمر ليس فقط غير أخلاقي إلى حد كبير، بل إنه غير قانوني.
In 2008, I went to Afghanistan
توجهت في عام 2008 إلى أفغانستان
for a justice funded program,
من أجل برنامج ممول للعدالة،
and I went there originally on this nine-month program
و بالأصل توجهت ضمن برنامج مدته تسعة شهور
to train Afghan lawyers.
لتدريب المحامين الأفغان.
In that nine months, I went around the country
خلال الشهور التسعة، تجولت في البلاد
and I talked to hundreds of people that were locked up,
و تحدثت إلى المئات من الأشخاص الذين كانوا متحفظين،
and I talked to many businesses
و تحدثت إلى العديد من الشركات
that were also operating in Afghanistan.
التي كانت تعمل في أفغانستان.
And within these conversations,
و في هذه المحادثات،
I started hearing the connections
بدأت أسمع المحادثات
between the businesses and the people,
بين الشركات و الناس،
and how laws that were meant to protect them
و كيف أن القوانين التي وضعت لحمايتهم
were being underused,
يتم معاملتها بسطحية،
while gross and illegal punitive measures were overused.
بينما كان يتم الإفراط في استعمال إجراءات العقاب الفادحة و غير الشرعية.
And so this put me on a quest for justness,
و هذا ما وضعني في رحلة بحث عن العدالة،
and what justness means to me
و ما تعنيه العدالة بالنسبة لي
is using laws for their intended purpose,
هو استخدام القوانين لأهدافها المقصودة،
which is to protect.
و هي الحماية.
The role of laws is to protect.
إن دور القوانين هي أن تحمي.
So as a result, I decided to open up a private practice,
إذن و نتيجة لذلك، قررت أن أفتتح مكتب محاماة خاص،
and I became the first foreigner to litigate
و أصبحت أول أجنبي يرفع دعوى
in Afghan courts.
في المحاكم الأفغانية.
Throughout this time, I also studied many laws,
و خلال هذا الوقت، درست الكثير من القوانين،
I talked to many people,
تحدثت إلى الكثير من الأشخاص،
I read up on many cases,
قرأت عن كثير من الحالات،
and I found that the lack of justness
و وجدت أن نقص العدالة
is not just a problem in Afghanistan,
ليس مشكلة في أفغانستان فحسب،
but it's a global problem.
بل مشكلة عالمية.
And while I originally shied away from
و بينما تورعت في الحقيقة عن
representing human rights cases
تمثيل حالات حقوق الإنسان
because I was really concerned about how it would
لأنني كنت قلقة حقاً حول كيف
affect me both professionally and personally,
ستلقي عليّ بظلالها على الصعيد المهني والشخصي
I decided that the need for justness was so great
قررت أن الحاجة للعدالة كانت كبيرة جداً
that I couldn't continue to ignore it.
حتى أنني لم أستطع مواصلة تجاهلها.
And so I started representing people like Naghma
و لذا بدأت بتمثيل أشخاص كـ(نغمة)
pro bono also.
و بدون مقابل.
Now, since I've been in Afghanistan
مذ كنت في أفغانستان
and since I've been an attorney for over 10 years,
و منذ أصبحت محامية لأكثر من عشر سنوات،
I've represented from CEOs of Fortune 500 companies
قد قمت بتمثيل أشخاص من مدراء تنفيذيين لـ 500 شركة غنية
to ambassadors to little girls like Naghma,
إلى سفراء، وفتيات صغيرات كـ(نغمة)
and with much success.
و بنجاح كبير.
And the reason for my success is very simple:
و سبب نجاحي بسيط جداً:
I work the system from the inside out
أعمل على النظام من الداخل إلى الخارج
and use the laws in the ways
و أستخدم القوانين بالطريقة
that they're intended to be used.
التي وضعت من أجلها.
I find that
أجد أن...
achieving justness in places like Afghanistan
تحقيق العدالة في أماكن كأفغانستان
is difficult, and there's three reasons.
هو أمر صعب، لثلاثة أسباب.
The first reason is that simply put,
السبب الأول و ببساطة،
people are very uneducated as to what their legal rights were,
الناس غير متعلمين نهائياً فيما يتعلق بماهية حقوقهم المشروعة،
and I find that this is a global problem.
و أجد هذا مشكلة عالمية.
The second issue
الأمر الثاني
is that even with laws on the books,
هو أنه و مع وجود القوانين في الكتب،
it's often superseded or ignored
يتم في الغالب إبطالها أو تجاهلها
by tribal customs, like in the first jirga
بالعادات القبلية، كما في الجيرغا الأول
that sold Naghma off.
التي بيعت (نغمة) من خلالها
And the third problem with achieving justness
والمشكلة الثالثة مع تحقيق العدالة
is that even with good, existing laws on the books,
هي أنه حتى مع القوانين الجيدة الموجودة في الكتب،
there aren't people or lawyers that are willing to fight
ليس هناك أشخاص أو محامين مستعدين للقتال
for those laws.
من أجل هذه القوانين.
And that's what I do: I use existing laws,
و هذا ما أفعله: أستخدم القوانين الموجودة،
often unused laws,
في الغالب القوانين غير المستعملة،
and I work those to the benefits of my clients.
و أستعملها لمصلحة موكلي.
We all need to create a global culture
علينا جميعاً أن ننشئ ثقافة عالمية
of human rights
لحقوق الإنسان
and be investors in a global human rights economy,
و أن نكون مستثمرين في إقتصاد حقوق الإنسان العالمي،
and by working in this mindset,
و بالعمل بطريقة التفكير هذه،
we can significantly improve justice globally.
بإمكاننا أن نحسن مستوى العدالة العالمية بشكل ملحوظ.
Now let's get back to Naghma.
لنعود إلى (نغمة)
Several people heard about this story,
سمع أناس كثر عن هذه القصة،
and so they contacted me because they wanted
و لذا اتصلوا بي لأنهم أرادوا
to pay the $2,500 debt.
أن يدفعوا قرض الـ 2,500 دولار.
And it's not just that simple;
و ليس ذلك بالأمر الهين؛
you can't just throw money at this problem
ليس بإمكانك فقط أن تقذف بالمال على هذه المشكلة
and think that it's going to disappear.
و تعتقد أنها ستختفي.
That's not how it works in Afghanistan.
ليس هكذا تسير الأمور في أفغانستان.
So I told them I'd get involved,
إذن أخبرتهم أنني سأتدخل،
but in order to get involved, what needed to happen
و لكن حتى أتدخل، ما كان ينبغي حدوثه
is a second jirga needed to be called,
هو جيرغا آخر يجب استدعائه،
a jirga of appeals.
جيرغا الاستئناف.
And so in order for that to happen,
و من أجل أن يحصل هذا،
we needed to get the village elders together,
احتجنا أن نجمع كبار القرية سوياً،
we needed to get the tribal leaders together,
احتجنا أن نجمع قادة العشائر سوياً،
the religious leaders.
الزعماء الدينيون.
Naghma's father needed to agree,
كان ينبغي أن يوافق والد نغمة،
the neighbor needed to agree,
كان ينبغي أن يوافق الجار،
and also his son needed to agree.
و كان ينبغي أن يوافق ابنه.
And I thought, if I'm going to get involved in this thing,
و فكرت، إذا كنت سأتدخل في هذا الأمر،
then they also need to agree that I preside over it.
إذاً عليهم أن يوافقوا على أن أترأس الجلسة.
So, after hours of talking
و بعد ساعات من الحديث
and tracking them down,
و اللحاق بهم،
and about 30 cups of tea,
و حوالي 30 كوب شاي،
they finally agreed that we could sit down
وافقوا أخيراً على أن بإمكاننا الجلوس
for a second jirga, and we did.
من أجل جيرغا ثانٍ، و فعلنا ذلك.
And what was different about the second jirga
و الذي كان مختلفاً بشأن الجيرغا الثاني
is this time, we put the law at the center of it,
في هذه المرة، أننا وضعنا القانون في محور الأمر كله،
and it was very important for me
و كان مهماً جداً بالنسبة لي
that they all understood that Naghma
أن الجميع فهم أن لنغمة
had a right to be protected.
الحق في الحماية.
And at the end of this jirga,
و في نهاية مجلس الجيرغا هذا،
it was ordered by the judge
كان الأمر من القاضي
that the first decision was erased,
بمحو القرار الأول،
and that the $2,500 debt was satisfied,
و أنه تم القبول برد مبلغ الـ 2,500 دولار،
and we all signed a written order
و قمنا جميعاً بتوقيع أمر مكتوب
where all the men acknowledged
حيث اعترف جميع الرجال
that what they did was illegal,
بأن ما فعلوه لم يكن شرعياً،
and if they did it again, that they would go to prison.
و بأنهم إن فعلوا ذلك مرة أخرى، سيذهبون إلى السجن.
Most —
الأكثر -
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thanks.
شكراً.
And most importantly,
و الأكثر أهمية،
the engagement was terminated
تم فسخ الخطوبة
and Naghma was free.
واستعادت (نغمة) حريتها
Protecting Naghma and her right to be free
إن حماية (نغمة) وحقها في أن تكون حرة
protects us.
يحمينا.
Now, with my job, there's above-average
الآن هناك كمية فوق المعدل
amount of risks that are involved.
من المخاطر يتضمنها ذلك.
I've been temporarily detained.
قد تم اعتقالي مؤقتاً.
I've been accused of running a brothel,
قد اتُهمت بإدارة بيت دعارة،
accused of being a spy.
و اتهمت بأنني جاسوسة.
I've had a grenade thrown at my office.
قد تم رمي قنبلة في مكتبي.
It didn't go off, though.
وذلك لم يثنيني عن العمل،
But I find that with my job,
و لكنني أجد أنه مع عملي،
that the rewards far outweigh the risks,
فإن المكافآت لا تذكر بالنسبة للمخاطر،
and as many risks as I take,
و بعدد المخاطر التي ألقاها،
my clients take far greater risks,
يتحمل الموكل مخاطر أعظم بكثير،
because they have a lot more to lose
فثمة الكثير ليخسره
if their cases go unheard,
إن لم يستمع أحد لقضيته
or worse, if they're penalized for having me as their lawyer.
أو أسوأ من ذلك، إن تم إلحاق العقوبة به لأني محاميته
With every case that I take,
و مع كل قضية أتولاها،
I realize that as much as I'm standing behind my clients,
أدرك أنه بقدر دعمي لموكلي،
that they're also standing behind me,
فهو أيضاً يدعمني،
and that's what keeps me going.
و هذا ما يدفعني إلى مواصلة الطريق.
Law as a point of leverage
إن القانون كنقطة للقوة
is crucial in protecting all of us.
مهم في حمايتنا جميعاً.
Journalists are very vital in making sure
إن الصحفيين مهمون جداً في التأكد
that that information is given to the public.
من أن المعلومات تصل إلى العامة.
Too often, we receive information from journalists
و غالباً، نستقبل المعلومات من الصحفيين
but we forget how that information was given.
و لكننا ننسى كيف وصلت المعلومات.
This picture is a picture of the
هذه الصورة
British press corps in Afghanistan.
لطاقم صحفي بريطاني في أفغانستان.
It was taken a couple of years ago by my friend David Gill.
قام صديقي (ديفيد جيل) بالتقاطها منذ عدة سنوات.
According to the Committee to Protect Journalists,
ووفقاً للجنة حماية الصحفيين،
since 2010, there have been thousands of journalists
فمنذ 2010، تعرض آلاف الصحفيين
who have been threatened, injured,
للتهديد والإصابات
killed, detained.
والقتل والاعتقال
Too often, when we get this information,
و غالباً، عندما تصلنا هذه المعلومات،
we forget who it affects
فإننا ننسى من تؤثر عليهم
or how that information is given to us.
أو كيف تصلنا تلك المعلومات.
What many journalists do, both foreign and domestic,
ما يفعله العديد من الصحفيين، الأجانب والمحليين،
is very remarkable, especially in places like Afghanistan,
هو عمل مثير للإعجاب، و خصوصاً في أماكن كأفغانستان،
and it's important that we never forget that,
و من المهم ألا ننسى ذلك،
because what they're protecting
لأن ما يقومون بحمايته
is not only our right to receive that information
ليس حقنا في تلقي هذه المعلومات فحسب
but also the freedom of the press, which is vital
بل حرية الصحافة أيضاً، و هي مهمة
to a democratic society.
بالنسبة إلى المجتمع الديمقراطي.
Matt Rosenberg is a journalist in Afghanistan.
(مات روزنبرغ) هو صحفي في أفغانستان.
He works for The New York Times,
إنه يعمل لجريدة نيويورك تايمز،
and unfortunately, a few months ago
و لسوء الحظ، قبل أشهر قلائل
he wrote an article that displeased
كتب مقالاً أثار استياء
people in the government.
أشخاص في الحكومة.
As a result, he was temporarily detained
و نتيجة لذلك، تم اعتقاله مؤقتاً
and he was illegally exiled out of the country.
و نفيه خارج البلاد.
I represent Matt,
أنا أمثل (مات)،
and after dealing with the government,
و بعد التعامل مع الحكومة،
I was able to get legal acknowledgment
كنت قادرة على الحصول على إقرار قانوني
that in fact he was illegally exiled,
بأن نفيه في الحقيقة غير قانوني،
and that freedom of the press does exist in Afghanistan,
و أن هناك حرية صحافة في أفغانستان،
and there's consequences if that's not followed.
و هناك عواقب إن لم يتم اتباع القوانين.
And I'm happy to say that
و أنا سعيدة لأقول
as of a few days ago,
في الأيام القليلة الماضية،
the Afghan government
قامت الحكومة الأفغانية
formally invited him back into the country
بدعوته رسمياً إلى العودة إلى البلاد
and they reversed their exile order of him.
و أنهم تراجعوا عن قرار نفيه.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
If you censor one journalist, then it intimidates others,
إن وضعت رقابة على صحفي واحد، فإن ذلك يخوف الآخرين،
and soon nations are silenced.
و بعد وقت قليل تصمت الأمم.
It's important that we protect our journalists
من المهم أن نحمي صحفيينا
and freedom of the press,
و حرية الصحافة،
because that makes governments more accountable to us
لأن ذلك يجعل الحكومات مسؤولة أكثر تجاهنا
and more transparent.
و أكثر شفافية.
Protecting journalists and our right
إن حماية الصحفيين و حقنا
to receive information protects us.
في استقبال المعلومات يحمينا.
Our world is changing. We live in a different world now,
إن عالمنا يتغير. نعيش في عالم مختلف الآن،
and what were once individual problems
و ما كان مرة مشاكل فردية
are really now global problems for all of us.
هي الآن في الحقيقة مشاكل عالمية بالنسبة لنا جميعاً.
Two weeks ago, Afghanistan had its first
قبل أسبوعين، حدث في أفغانستان
democratic transfer of power
أول انتقال ديمقراطي للسلطة
and elected president Ashraf Ghani, which is huge,
و انتخب الرئيس (أشرف غاني)، و هذه خطوة كبيرة،
and I'm very optimistic about him,
و أنا متفائلة جداً به،
and I'm hopeful that he'll give Afghanistan
و آمل أن يعطي أفغانستان
the changes that it needs,
التغيير الذي تحتاجه،
especially within the legal sector.
خصوصاً في القطاع القانوني.
We live in a different world.
نحن نعيش في عالم مختلف.
We live in a world where my eight-year-old daughter
نعيش في عالم حيث ابنتي ذات الثمان سنوات
only knows a black president.
تعرف رئيساً أسوداً فقط.
There's a great possibility that our next president
هناك احتمال كبير بأن رئيسنا التالي
will be a woman,
ستكون امرأة،
and as she gets older, she may question,
و عندما تكبر، ربما تتساءل،
can a white guy be president?
هل بإمكان شاب أبيض أن يصبح الرئيس؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Our world is changing, and we need to change with it,
إن عالمنا يتغير، و نحن بحاجة إلى التغير معه،
and what were once individual problems
و ما كانت يوماً مشاكل فردية
are problems for all of us.
هي مشاكل بالنسبة لنا جميعاً.
According to UNICEF,
حسب منظمة الأمم المتحدة للطفولة،
there are currently over 280 million
فإن هناك أكثر من 280 مليون
boys and girls who are married
طفل وطفلة متزوجين
under the age of 15.
و هم تحت عمر 15 سنة.
Two hundred and eighty million.
مئتان و ثماني ملايين.
Child marriages prolong the vicious cycle
زواج الأطفال يطيل الدورة الخبيثة
of poverty, poor health, lack of education.
للفقر والمستوى الرديء للصحة و نقص التعليم.
At the age of 12, Sahar was married.
في عمر 12 سنة، تزوجت (سحر)
She was forced into this marriage
تم اجبارها على هذا الزواج
and sold by her brother.
و بيعها على يد أخوها.
When she went to her in-laws' house,
عندما ذهبت إلى بيت عائلتها الجديدة،
they forced her into prostitution.
أجبروها على الدعارة.
Because she refused, she was tortured.
و لأنها رفضت، تم تعذيبها.
She was severely beaten with metal rods.
ضربت بشدة بواسطة قضبان من الحديد.
They burned her body.
حرقوا جثتها.
They tied her up in a basement and starved her.
قيّدوها في القبو وتركوها جائعة
They used pliers to take out her fingernails.
استخدموا الكماشات لخلع أظفارها.
At one point,
و في لحظة ما،
she managed to escape from this torture chamber
استطاعت الهرب من غرفة التعذيب هذه
to a neighbor's house,
إلى بيت الجار،
and when she went there, instead of protecting her,
و عندما ذهبت هناك، بدلاً من حمايتها،
they dragged her back
أعادوها سحباً
to her husband's house,
إلى بيت زوجها،
and she was tortured even worse.
و تم تعذيبها بشكل أسوأ من ذي قبل.
When I met first Sahar, thankfully,
عندما التقيت سحر، لحسن الحظ،
Women for Afghan Women
قامت جمعية "نساء من أجل المرأة الأفغانية"
gave her a safe haven to go to.
بإعطائها ملاذاً آمناً للذهاب إليه.
As a lawyer, I try to be very strong
و كمحامية، أحاول أن أكون قوية جداً
for all my clients,
أمام كل موكل لدي،
because that's very important to me,
لأن ذلك مهم جداً بالنسبة لي،
but seeing her,
و لكن رؤيتها،
how broken and very weak as she was,
كيف كانت مكسورة الخاطر و ضعيفة جداً،
was very difficult.
كانت رؤيتها صعبة جداً.
It took weeks for us to really get to
استغرقتُ أسبوعين حتى أفهم بحق
what happened to her
ماذا حدث لها
when she was in that house,
عندما كانت في ذلك المنزل،
but finally she started opening up to me,
و لكنها في نهاية المطاف بدأت بمحادثة من القلب معي،
and when she opened up,
و عندما فعلت ذلك،
what I heard was
ما سمعته هو أنها
she didn't know what her rights were,
لم تكن تعلم ماهية حقوقها،
but she did know she had a certain level of protection
و لكنها علمت أن لها درجة معينة من الحماية
by her government that failed her,
عند حكومتها التي خذلتها
and so we were able to talk about
و بذلك كنا قادرين على الحديث معها
what her legal options were.
عن الخيارات القانونية المتاحة بالنسبة لها.
And so we decided to take this case
و قررنا أخذ هذه القضية
to the Supreme Court.
إلى المحكمة العليا.
Now, this is extremely significant,
الآن، هذا مهم جداً،
because this is the first time
لأن هذه هي المرة الأولى
that a victim of domestic violence in Afghanistan
أن ضحية عنف منزلي في أفغانستان
was being represented by a lawyer,
يتم تمثيلها بواسطة محام،
a law that's been on the books for years and years,
قانون كان موجوداً في الكتب لسنوات و سنوات،
but until Sahar, had never been used.
و لكنه لم يتم استخدامه حتى قضية (سحر)
In addition to this, we also decided
و بالإضافة إلى ذلك، قررنا أيضاً
to sue for civil damages,
أن نقاضيهم على الأضرار المدنية،
again using a law that's never been used,
مرة أخرى بواسطة قانون لم يُستخدم من قبل،
but we used it for her case.
و لكننا استخدمناه من أجل قضيتها.
So there we were at the Supreme Court
إذن كنا هناك في المحكمة العليا
arguing in front of 12 Afghan justices,
نتجادل أمام 12 من القضاة الأفغان،
me as an American female lawyer,
أنا كمحامية أمريكية أنثى،
and Sahar, a young woman
و(سحر)، المرأة الشابة
who when I met her couldn't speak above a whisper.
التي عندما قابلتها لم تستطع رفع صوتها أعلى من الهمس.
She stood up,
وَقَفَتْ
she found her voice,
وَجَدَتْ صوتها،
and my girl told them that she wanted justice,
و قالت لهم فتاتي بأنها أرادت العدالة،
and she got it.
و حصلت عليها.
At the end of it all, the court unanimously agreed
و في نهاية ذلك كله، وافقت المحكمة بالاجماع
that her in-laws should be arrested for what they did to her,
بأنه ينبغي اعتقال عائلتها الجديدة جراء ما ارتكبوه بحقها،
her fucking brother should also be arrested
و أن أخاها المعتوه يجب يُعتقل أيضاً
for selling her —
لأنه قام ببيعها -
(Applause) —
(تصفيق) -
and they agreed that she did have a right
و وافقوا أيضاً على أن لديها حقاً
to civil compensation.
بالحصول على التعويض المدني.
What Sahar has shown us is that we can attack
أظهرت لنا (سحر) إمكانية محاربة
existing bad practices by using the laws
الممارسات السيئة الموجودة باستخدام القوانين
in the ways that they're intended to be used,
بالطرق التي وجدت لتستخدم بها،
and by protecting Sahar,
و بحماية (سحر)،
we are protecting ourselves.
فإننا نحمي أنفسنا.
After having worked in Afghanistan
و بعد العمل في أفغانستان،
for over six years now,
لمدة تزيد عن الست سنوات الآن،
a lot of my family and friends think
الكثير من أفراد عائلتي و أصدقائي يعتقدون
that what I do looks like this.
بأن ما أفعله يبدو هكذا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But in all actuality, what I do looks like this.
و لكن في كل الحقيقة، ما أفعله يبدو هكذا.
Now, we can all do something.
بإمكاننا جميعاً أن نفعل شيئاً.
I'm not saying we should all buy a plane ticket and go to Afghanistan,
لا أقول بأن علينا أن نشتري تذكرة طائرة و نذهب إلى أفغانستان،
but we can all be contributors
و لكن بإمكاننا جميعاً أن نكون مساهمين
to a global human rights economy.
في إقتصاد حقوق الإنسان العالمي.
We can create a culture of transparency
بإمكاننا أن ننشيء ثقافة من الشفافية
and accountability to the laws,
و الإلتزام بالقانون،
and make governments more accountable to us,
و أن نجعل الحكومات أكثر التزاماً تجاهنا،
as we are to them.
كما نحن بالنسبة لهم.
A few months ago, a South African lawyer
منذ بضعة أشهر، محامٍ جنوب أفريقي
visited me in my office
قام بزيارتي في مكتبي
and he said, "I wanted to meet you.
و قال، "أردت لقائك.
I wanted to see what a crazy person looked like."
أردت رؤية الشخص المجنون الذي أنت عليه."
The laws are ours,
القوانين لنا،
and no matter what your ethnicity,
و مهما كانت إثنيتك
nationality, gender, race,
و جنسيتك ونوعك وعرقك،
they belong to us,
فإنها تنتمي لنا،
and fighting for justice is not an act of insanity.
و إن كفاحنا من أجل العدالة ليس ضرباً من الجنون.
Businesses also need to get with the program.
على الشركات أيضاً أن تلتحق بالبرنامج.
A corporate investment in human rights
إن استثمار شركة في مجال حقوق الإنسان
is a capital gain on your businesses,
هو ربح لرأس المال يضاف إلى شركاتكم،
and whether you're a business, an NGO,
و سواء أكنت شركة، منظمة أهلية،
or a private citizen, rule of law benefits all of us.
أو مواطناً يعمل في القطاع الخاص، فإن سلطة القانون تفيدنا جميعاً.
And by working together with a concerted mindset,
و بالعمل معاً بطريقة تفكير متفق عليها،
through the people, public and private sector,
بين الأشخاص و القطاع العام والخاص،
we can create a global human rights economy
فإن بإمكاننا أن ننشيء اقتصاد حقوق الإنسان العالمي
and all become global investors in human rights.
و نصبح جميعاً مستثمرين في حقوق الإنسان.
And by doing this,
و بفعل ذلك،
we can achieve justness together.
فإن بإمكاننا أن نحقق العدالة معاً.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)